Chicago Ethnic Arts Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 6: Sound Recordings, 1977
  - Subseries 15: Lithuanian
    - Interview with Vladas Polikauskas and Sophia Polikauskas, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-4, July 17, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20845A - AFS 20846B; RYA 0833-0834; 4 audiocassette, C-60; audiocassette, C-60
      Recording first segment, from the start to about 18:45 minutes elapsed time: part 3 of a 3-part recording of informal conversation and singing at an outdoor event at the Sisters of St. Casimir Motherhouse on Marquette Street; the main, continuing element is an interview-discussion with Sister Anne Marie [surname not documented], primarily in English, touching on topics like the role of the Lithuanian language in Chicago, and song books with hymns and other music in Lithuanian; overall the recording is casual and social, the recorder is turned off and on, and other voices of women and men are also heard, some speaking in Lithuanian, regularly interspersed with singing in Lithuanian; recording second segment, from about 18:45 minutes elapsed time to the end: part 1 of a 3-part recording of an interview in Lithuanian with Mr. and Mrs. Vladas and Sophia Polikauskas, at their home at 7212 [7217 ?] South Sawyer Ave., in the background of segments of this recording is the voice of a broadcast announces, in Lithuanian; the fieldworker's notes state that the topics include general discussion about Lithuanian community life in Chicago, and the Polikauskases' life stories. Part 2 of a 3-part recording of an interview in Lithuanian with Mr. and Mrs. Vladas and Sophia Polikauskas, at their home at 7212 [7217 ?] South Sawyer Ave., the fieldworker's notes state that the topics include general discussion about Lithuanian community life in Chicago, and the Polikauskases' life stories. Part 3 of a 4-part recording of an interview in Lithuanian with Mr. and Mrs. Vladas and Sophia Polikauskas, at their home at 7212 [7217 ?] South Sawyer Ave., the fieldworker's notes state that the topics include general discussion about Lithuanian community life in Chicago, and the Polikauskases' life stories. Part 4 of a 4-part recording of an interview in Lithuanian with Mr. and Mrs. Vladas and Sophia Polikauskas, at their home at 7212 [7217 ?] South Sawyer Ave., the fieldworker's notes state that the topics include general discussion about Lithuanian community life in Chicago, and the Polikauskases' life stories; this part has a duration of about 16:40 minutes.
  - Subseries 16: Yugoslavian
    - Recording of music performances at Europe at Night, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-6, June 26, 1977; July 02, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20847 - AFS 20852; RXA 1093-1098; 6 audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Part 1 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ? Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include "They Call the Wind Maria," male vocal; "Volga Boatman," male vocal; unnamed polka, male vocal; unnamed ballad, male vocal; "Sailor's Dance," instrumental; unnamed song led by accordion; unnamed song, with added tambourine; song medley including "Milord" (associated with Edith Piaf), waltz; dance piece featuring the accordion. Part 2 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ?, Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include "'Til There was You," piano solo; "Feelings," piano solo; unnamed song, piano and guitar (electric), tambourine; "By the Time I Get to Phoenix," piano, guitar; "Satin Doll," piano, guitar; "Alfie," piano, guitar, pianist calls out chords for the guitarist; "The Sunshine of My Life"; "Life's Eternal Springtime," sung in Serbian (?) and English; "Another little Irish number," with vocal; "The Day You Took My Hand" and "A Love Song," vocal, tape runs out before end of song. Part 3 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ?, Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include unnamed song, sung in Serbian (?); three unnamed songs with accordion featured as lead; song identified in notes a Tsarist Russian national anthem, male vocal; "Old Man River," vocal; "The Impossible Dream," vocal; "Dulcinea," vocal; unnamed song; unnamed instrumental, tape runs out before end of song. Part 4 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ?, Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include introduction by hostess; "Russian Songs," male vocal with joking banter with the audience; additional comments by hostess, says many in crowd are Jewish; "A Russian Song," male vocal with crowd clapping; additional comments by hostess, says many in crowd have heritage in other nations, introduces Vietnamese songs; "A Gypsy Song," male vocal; additional comments by hostess, says many in crowd have Hungarian heritage; "A Yiddish Song," male vocal; unnamed song, audience sings along; unnamed song featuring accordion; "Somewhere My Love" as instrumental featuring accordion; unnamed instrumental. Part 5 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ?, Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include instrumental medley that includes "Sunrise, Sunset"; two unnamed instrumentals; three unnamed songs sung in Italian; song in Italian from the "Barber of Seville"; unnamed song sung in Italian; all Italian vocals by Salvatore [?]. Part 6 of a 6-part recording of music performances at Europe at Night, 2986 Elston, Chicago; project notes refer to the venue as a Yugoslav displaced person nightclub, owned by accordion player Milija Spasojevich; project notes include fragments of band member names, [Slawko, Slavco ?], guitar; Larry Ekermann, piano; Salvatore [?], vocals; Eddie [Crackey, Kraki ?], vocals and master of ceremonies; [Tramiglia ?, Milija ?], accordion, guitar; in parts 4 and 6, a woman's voice is heard announcing and singing, referred to as "hostess"; selections in this part include unnamed song sung in Italian by Salvatore [?], tape begins with song in progress; "Moonlight Sonata" (Beethoven), Larry Eckermann, piano solo; unnamed song, featuring piano; medley of "Happy Birthday" and "Hail, Hail, the Gang's All Here" led by the hostess, followed by announcement of the length of marriage of some of the couples in the audience, followed by "Anniversary Waltz," sung by the hostess, audience response as couples are introduced and dance; instrumental dance piece; fox-trot medley of "Tea for Two" and "Never on Sunday"; unnamed song with tambourine added to ensemble.
  - Subseries 17: Russian
    - Interview with Gertrude Westphal about her history and her experiences teaching children, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-3, April 28, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20853A - AFS 20855A; RYA 0835-0837; 3 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 3-part interview with Gertrude Westphal by fieldworker Greta Swenson; topics include how Westphal got into early childhood education, low income children, mentored by Margaret Bush, librarian in Oak Park; about the role of the library, family story hours, she "tells" stories (not "reads"), importance of oral delivery, use in classroom; about the mental representation of education, images and imagination develop, children want a tale every day, reference to Bruno Bettleheim's Uses of Enchantment; about going from storytelling to dramatic play with costumes; importance of correct use of English; Cinderella is a favorite; about a girl who used "classroom English on stage, praise led children to group-goal oriented; explanation of the Child-Parent Center operation, the operation here reflects parent concern with language, desire from small groups, like a one-room schoolhouse; how imagination for writing comes from story telling, visit grandparents in the South on farms, led to story writing by students with an audience in mind; language development toward "proper" English important for low income children to find jobs later; importance of folklore (folk tales) with children, about Westphal's mother's influence; about the old country (Germany); Westphal learned German at home and English in school; about how Germans were unpopular in America in the period of the two wars and between; Westphal's maiden name is Schraut, led to teasing in U.S.; her father is (was?) a janitor in the Englewood area; only whites in a black neighborhood, then moved to white neighborhood and called "n----- lover." Part 2 of a 3-part interview with Gertrude Westphal by fieldworker Greta Swenson; topics include comments on the Schwaben Klub (Swabian Club), dances as a girl, polka, waltz; about German folksongs; Westphal had a white friend, they socialized with black girls, ghost tales, "steps and liver," "Mary Mack" (song for a clapping game), using rhythm when teaching (Westphal sings "Mary Mack"), "Hambone," and from her neighborhood, "Double Dutch" (played by black children), hopscotch; comments on the physical abilities of black and white children; about singing on Sunday at a Baptist church; Westphal grew up with gospel and polka; about "Zum Deutschen Eck" (famous Chicago German bierstube and restaurant) as authentic; about a German folksong learned from her father; about the German American community in Chicago, moved from the Near North Side; about Westphal's work in schools, always in all-black schools, when she raised her family, she spent 17 and a half years not teaching, then went into early childhood teaching, work at the Child-Parent Center on North Lawndale, served low income African American families; good support from principal, need to offer assurances of justice and law and order for children, the class is not "open" at first, but is later after children learn to structure their time and develop a community spirit; method depended on storytelling, giving of self and values through fairy tales, there are moral judgements in the tales, "justice will come"; Westphal uses classic folktales, Cinderella, no crime stories, which would be retelling news accounts of crime in the neighborhood; parents are protective, this is a high crime area, children kept in the house, parents take them to visit friends, families do not have the means to move away; story about a child missed school after the mother in a downstairs apartment murdered her child; migration from the South is over for blacks, during the 1950s we had a new kid class every week; the families all go South to home for Thanksgiving and Christmas, many have farm experience, a popular book is Blaze [possibly the C.W. Anderson series ?], kids like horse stories; these families do not know Chicago, arts opportunities not used, they visit family and friends and are active in churches; comments on collecting. Part 3 of a 3-part interview with Gertrude Westphal by fieldworker Greta Swenson; topics include comments on the Schwaben Klub (Swabian Club), dances as a girl, polka, waltz; about German folksongs; Westphal had a white friend, they socialized with black girls, ghost tales, "steps and liver," "Mary Mack" (song for a clapping game), using rhythm when teaching (Westphal sings "Mary Mack"), "Hambone," and from her neighborhood, "Double Dutch" (played by black children), hopscotch; comments on the physical abilities of black and white children; about singing on Sunday at a Baptist church; Westphal grew up with gospel and polka; about "Zum Deutschen Eck" (famous Chicago German bierstube and restaurant) as authentic; about a German folksong learned from her father; about the German American community in Chicago, moved from the Near North Side; about Westphal's work in schools, always in all-black schools, when she raised her family, she spent 17 and a half years not teaching, then went into early childhood teaching, work at the Child-Parent Center on North Lawndale, served low income African American families; good support from principal, need to offer assurances of justice and law and order for children, the class is not "open" at first, but is later after children learn to structure their time and develop a community spirit; method depended on storytelling, giving of self and values through fairy tales, there are moral judgements in the tales, "justice will come"; Westphal uses classic folktales, Cinderella, no crime stories, which would be retelling news accounts of crime in the neighborhood; parents are protective, this is a high crime area, children kept in the house, parents take them to visit friends, families do not have the means to move away; story about a child missed school after the mother in a downstairs apartment murdered her child; migration from the South is over for blacks, during the 1950s we had a new kid class every week; the families all go South to home for Thanksgiving and Christmas, many have farm experience, a popular book is Blaze [possibly the C.W. Anderson series ?], kids like horse stories; these families do not know Chicago, arts opportunities not used, they visit family and friends and are active in churches; comments on collecting.
    - Interview with Paul Hummer of Chicago Fine Arts Council, Chicago, Illinois, June 20, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20856; RYA 0838; audiocassette, C-60
      Discussion between Paul Hummer, representing the city of Chicago's Fine Arts Council and fieldworker (and on-site project administrator) Greta Swenson about ethnic folk art and folk expression and how or when this might be a fit for support from the Fine Arts Council; the recording is marred for a few seconds before and after the discussion by a loud electrical noise; in the recording of the discussion, there is a residual hum with the voices off-mike; duration 33 minutes.
    - Recording of the Chicago Irish Musicians Association Annual Concert, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-3, June 25, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20857 - AFS 20858; RYA 0839-0840; 3 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 3-part recording of the Irish Musicians Fourth Annual Concert at Bogan High School Auditorium, 7900 South Pulaski Road; poor sound quality due to problems with public address system in the auditorium and placement of fieldworker's audiocassette recorder in the audience area; the fieldworker's notes indicate the radio announcer Tom McNamara served as master of ceremonies, and state that families attended with younger children but no teenagers or young people in their 20s; the mimeographed program for the event lists artists but the exact sequence may or may not have been followed; likely performers in this part may include full band, reels and jigs; dancing school, Jerry O'Loughlin; song, Bill Cody and Jim Thornton; champion accordion player, Jimmy Keane; dancing school, Mae Kennedy Kane; song, Jack Finan and Jimmy Keane Sr. Part 2 of a 3-part recording of the Irish Musicians Fourth Annual Concert at Bogan High School Auditorium, 7900 South Pulaski Road; imperfect sound quality due to problems with public address system in the auditorium and placement of fieldworker's audiocassette recorder in the audience area; the fieldworker's notes indicate the radio announcer Tom McNamara served as master of ceremonies, and state that families attended with younger children but no teenagers or young people in their 20s; the mimeographed program for the event lists artists but the exact sequence may or may not have been followed; likely performers in this part may include violin champion, Johnny McGreevy; dancing school, Barbara McNulty; duet Fleadh Ceoil champions, Steve Trent and Mary Cloonan; the Noel Gaffney Group; Kevin Henry family (two daughters, one son); champion dancers, Flatley brothers; full band; champion Fleadh Ceoil singer, Mary Cooley; dancing school, Toni Weber-Brown; duet, Seamus Cooley and Pat Burke. Part 3 of a 3-part recording of the Irish Musicians Fourth Annual Concert at Bogan High School Auditorium, 7900 South Pulaski Road; imperfect sound quality due to problems with public address system in the auditorium and placement of fieldworker's audiocassette recorder in the audience area; the fieldworker's notes indicate the radio announcer Tom McNamara served as master of ceremonies, and state that families attended with younger children but no teenagers or young people in their 20s; the mimeographed program for the event lists artists but the exact sequence may or may not have been followed; the initial performance is an unaccompanied song by an unidentified female singer; other possible performers in this part may include Fleadh Ceoil singer Jimmy Fahey; dancing school, Jerry O'Loughlin; Fleadh Ceoil lilting champions, Tom McMahon and Maggie Henry (age 10); the Noel Gaffney Group; champion dancers, the Flatley brothers; song, Martin O'Brien and Maggie Henry; duet on flute and spoons, Tom Masterson Sr and Jr; finale, full band.
    - Jam session in a bar following the Chicago Irish Musicians Annual Concert, Chicago, Illinois, June 25, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20858_02; RYA 0840; audiocassette, C-60
      Recording made in a bar at 6511 South Kedzie (may have been named Frank's or Flanagan's), following the Irish Musicians Fourth Annual Concert at Bogan High School Auditorium, 7900 South Pulaski Road; the fieldworker's notes state that she was invited to attend this back room session by Johnny McGreevy and Tom McMahon; they were joined in their music by 10-year-old Maggie Henry, described as "trying out various instruments."
    - Recording of a Saturday evening vespers at Holy Trinity Orthodox Cathedral, in English, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, July 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20859 - AFS 20859_02; RYA 0841; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1-2 of a 2-part recording of vespers at Holy Trinity Orthodox Cathedral, 1121 North Leavitt. The priest is identified as Father Kuberski; this service was attended by project fieldworkers Jonas Dovydenas, Elena Bradunas, Greta Swenson, and Carl Fleischhauer, with support from Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa; project notes sometimes give the date as July 8, 1977; assuming the service was on Saturday, the correct date is July 9.
    - Conversation with Gordana Trbuhovic, Father Kuberski, other Holy Trinity Orthodox Cathdral members, Chicago, Illinois, July 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20860; RYA 0842; audiocassette, C-60
      Recording of informal conversation and snatches of song made after the vespers service at Holy Trinity Orthodox Cathedral, 1121 North Leavitt; duration 10:15 minutes. The priest is identified as Father Kuberski; this service was attended by project fieldworkers Jonas Dovydenas, Elena Bradunas, Greta Swenson, and Carl Fleischhauer, with support from Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa. Project notes sometimes give the date as July 8, 1977; assuming the service was on Saturday, the correct date is July 9.
  - Subseries 18: Media Coverage
    - Antony Hellenberg and Sara Schwarz on WBBM, Chicago, Illinois, April 22, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20861; RYA 0843; audiocassette, C-60
    - Jack Hafferkamp radio spot promoting awareness of the Chicago Ethnic Arts Project, June 15, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20862_01; RYA 0844; audiocassette, C-60
  - Subseries 19: Demonstration Tapes
    - Selected sound recordings, reel I, Chicago Ethnic Arts Project, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20864; RXA 1353; audiotape reel, 7 in.
      The tapes with the title "Demonstration Tape" are recorded samples of excerpts from various interviews and performances recorded in this collection.
    - Selected sound recordings, reel II, Chicago Ethnic Arts Project, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20865; RXA 1354; audiotape reel, 7 in.
    - Selected sound recordings, reel III, Chicago Ethnic Arts Project, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20866; RXA 1355; audiotape reel, 7 in.
    - Selected sound recordings, reel IV, Chicago Ethnic Arts Project, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20867; RXA 1356; audiotape reel, 7 in.
- Series 7: Graphic Materials, 1977
  - Subseries 1: Color slides and negatives
    - Greek
      - St. Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan, Chicago, Illinois, April 18, 1977, AFC 1981/004: 001; Carl Fleischhauer; 16 35mm color slides
        Image numbers, descriptions: 1-5, exterior of St. Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan, Chicago; 6-17, interior of church, series of photographs taken progressively closer to altar
      - St. Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan, Chicago, Illinois, April 18, 1977, AFC 1981/004: 002; Carl Fleischhauer; 19 35mm color slides
        Image numbers, descriptions: 1-2, painting by Bob Clark and Andy Karafatias in gym of St. Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan Rd., Chicago; 3-11, close-ups of painting; 12-19, series of paintings on wall in gym by Dean Pappas (G.O.Y.A. - Greek Orthodox Youth Association).
      - Rev. Peter C. Karloutsos, St. Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan, Chicago, Illinois, May 18, 1977, AFC 1981/004: 003; Carl Fleischhauer; 3 35 mm color slide
        Image numbers, descriptions: 1-3 Rev. Peter C. Karloutsos in his office, St, Andrew's Greek Orthodox Church, 5649 N. Sheridan, Chicago.
      - Icon painting, Stathis Trahanatzis, iconographer, Chicago, Illinois, April 21, 1977, AFC 1981/004: 004; Carl Fleischhauer; 20 35 mm color slide
        Image numbers, descriptions: 1-10, large icon in studio of Stathis Trahanatzis, iconographer, 7007 N. Ridge Blvd., Chicago; 11-13, painting materials; 14-16, chest in living room; 17-19, living room wall - paintings are directly on the wall; 20, decorated shells and pebbles - paintings will be added in the white spaces.
      - Icon painting, Stathis Trahanatzis, iconographer, Chicago, Illinois, April 21, 1977, AFC 1981/004: 005; Carl Fleischhauer; 20 35 mm color slide